Guide to the Nuclear Free America Records 1945-2003
Oregon State University Libraries, Special Collections and Archives Research Center
- Nuclear Free Zones Project, 1981-1995; Series 2
  - United States Zones, 1982-1995
    - New York - Monroe County - Rochester, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 8.20)
    - New York - New York City, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 8.21)
    - New York - New York Harbor, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 8.22)
    - New York - New York Harbor, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 8.23)
    - North Carolina, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 9.01)
    - North Dakota, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 9.02)
    - Ohio, 1993 (Box-folder 9.03)
    - Ohio, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 9.04)
    - Ohio, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 9.05)
    - Ohio, undated (Box-folder 9.06)
    - Ohio, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 9.07)
    - Ohio - Scioto, 1981 (Box-folder 9.08)
    - Oklahoma, 1985 (Box-folder 9.09)
    - Oregon, undated (Box-folder 9.10)
    - Oregon, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 9.11)
    - Oregon - Columbia County - Trojan Nuclear Power Plant, 1992-1995 (Box-folder 9.12)
    - Oregon - Coos County, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 9.13)
    - Oregon - Lane County, undated (Box-folder 9.14)
    - Oregon - Lane County - Eugene, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 9.15)
    - Oregon - Marion County - Salem, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 9.16)
    - Oregon - Multnomah County - Portland, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 9.17)
    - Oregon - Multnomah County - Portland, 1983-1990 (Box-folder 9.18)
    - Pennsylvania, undated (Box-folder 9.19)
    - Pennsylvania, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 10.01)
    - Pennsylvania, 1987-1992 (Box-folder 10.02)
    - Rhode Island, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 10.03)
    - South Carolina, 1987 (Box-folder 10.04)
    - South Dakota, 1983 (Box-folder 10.05)
    - Tennessee, 1980-1988 (Box-folder 10.06)
    - Texas, undated (Box-folder 10.07)
    - Utah, undated (Box-folder 10.08)
    - Vermont, 1983-1994 (Box-folder 10.09)
    - Virginia, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 10.10)
    - Washington, undated (Box-folder 10.11)
    - Washington, 1984-1990 (Box-folder 10.12)
    - Washington, undated (Box-folder 10.13)
    - Washington - Okanogan County, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 10.14)
    - Washington - Whatcom County, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 10.15)
    - Washington, D.C., 1985-1992 (Box-folder 10.16)
    - West Virginia, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 10.17)
    - Wisconsin, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 10.18)
    - Wyoming, undated (Box-folder 10.19)
    - United States Virgin Islands, 1986 (Box-folder 10.20)
  - Native Lands (United States) Zones, 1984-1995
    - Nuclear Free Indian Lands Project, undated (Box-folder 10.21)
    - Nuclear Free Indian Lands Project, undated (Box-folder 10.22)
    - Nuclear Free Indian Lands Project, undated (Box-folder 10.23)
    - Nuclear Free Indian Lands Project, undated (Box-folder 10.24)
    - Nuclear Free Indian Lands Project, undated (Box-folder 10.25)
    - Native lands - Alaska, undated (Box-folder 11.01)
    - Native lands - Arizona, 1991-1993 (Box-folder 11.02)
    - Native lands - California, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 11.03)
    - Native lands - Kansas, undated (Box-folder 11.04)
    - Native lands - Minnesota, 1994 (Box-folder 11.05)
    - Native lands - Montana, 1984-1993 (Box-folder 11.06)
    - Native lands - New Mexico, undated (Box-folder 11.07)
    - Native lands - New Mexico, undated (Box-folder 11.08)
    - Native lands - Nevada, 1991-1995 (Box-folder 11.09)
    - Native lands - New York, 1994 (Box-folder 11.10)
    - Native lands - North Dakota, 1994 (Box-folder 11.11)
    - Native lands - Oklahoma, 1994 (Box-folder 11.12)
    - Native lands - Oregon, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 11.13)
    - Native lands - South Dakota, 1994 (Box-folder 11.14)
    - Native lands - Washington, undated (Box-folder 11.15)
    - Native lands - Wisconsin, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 11.16)
    - Native lands - Wyoming, undated (Box-folder 11.17)
  - International Zones, 1961-1994
    - African Zone, 1961-1994 (Box-folder 11.18)
    - Antarctic Zone, undated (Box-folder 11.19)
    - Arctic Zone, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 11.20)
    - Arctic Zone, undated (Box-folder 11.21)
    - Asian Zone, 1986-1993 (Box-folder 11.22)
    - Balkan Zone, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 11.23)
    - Eastern European Zone, undated (Box-folder 11.24)
    - European Zone, 1990 (Box-folder 11.25)
    - European Zone, undated (Box-folder 11.26)
    - Indian Ocean Zone, undated (Box-folder 11.27)
    - Latin America Zone, 1984-1994 (Box-folder 11.28)
    - Mediterranean Zone, undated (Box-folder 11.29)
    - Middle East Zone, 1992 (Box-folder 11.30)
    - Nordic Zone, 1983-1989 (Box-folder 11/31)
    - South Pacific Nuclear Free Zone, 1984-1989 (Box-folder 11.32)
    - Algeria, undated (Box-folder 11.33)
    - Argentina, undated (Box-folder 11.34)
    - Australia, 1994 (Box-folder 11.35)
    - Brazil, 1990 (Box-folder 11.36)
    - Canada, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 11.37)
    - France, 1993 (Box-folder 11.38)
    - Germany, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 11.39)
    - Japan, undated (Box-folder 11.40)
    - Japan, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 12.01)
    - Korea, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 12.02)
    - New Zealand, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 12.03)
    - Philippines, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 12.04)
    - Russia/USSR, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 12.05)
    - United Kingdom, undated (Box-folder 12.06)
- Weapons-Maker Database, 1986-2001; Series 3
  Series 3 documents an important product of Nuclear Free America which was in high demand by activist groups for many years. The weapons-maker database compiled and cross-referenced numerous federal datasets to provide reports on the sources, materials, and makers of nuclear weapons in the United States. This database included Department of Defense and Department of Energy contracts for weapons systems and weapons systems support by contractor and parent company. These data were derived from the Federal Procurement Data Center’s Individual Contract Actions and Awards master file, and were combined with parent company data provided by Eagle Eye Publishers of Arlington, Virginia. Buyers of these data and reports, including individuals, organizations, and nonprofits, used them to prepare boycotts, educate consumers, and a variety of other legal and social uses. NFA published a top 100 and a top 50 nuclear weapons systems makers list annually, ranked by total contract amount from the U.S. government. Familiar corporations such as AT&T, Boeing, General Motors, General Electric, Ford Motor, Hewlett-Packard, Lockheed, and Westinghouse appear annually on each list ranked according to total amounts received. Materials include data sheets, correspondence with clients and data providers, a list of cross-reference codes, and compiled lists.
  - Contract negotiations, 1990 (Box-folder 12.07)
  - Data clients, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 12.08)
  - Data clients, 1992-2001 (Box-folder 12.09)
  - Data clients, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 12.10)
  - Eagle Eye Publishers, Inc., undated (Box-folder 12.11)
  - Kinder, Lydenberg, Domini, & Co., Inc., 1990-1993 (Box-folder 12.12)
  - U.S. Trust, 1991 (Box-folder 12.13)
  - NFA weapons codes, 1991 (Box-folder 12.14)
  - NFA weapons codes, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 12.15)
  - NFA weapons codes, undated (Box-folder 12.16)
  - Weapons contractors reports, 1986-1995 (Box-folder 12.17)
  - Weapons contractors - reference materials, 1987-1997 (Box-folder 12.18)
  - Weapons contractors - boycotts, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 12.19)
  - Weapons contractor data, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 12.20)
  - Parent companies of U.S. military contractors, fiscal year 1993 (Box-folder 12.21)
  - Parent companies of U.S. military contractors, fiscal year 1994 (Box-folder 13.01)
- Other Initiatives and Projects, 1979-1995; Series 4
  Series 4 compiles files on other Nuclear Free America projects, including those intended to increase public awareness of consumer links to the nuclear arms race and to provide people with simple ways of taking action against nuclear weapons contractors. The boycott of Morton Salt (whose parent company Morton Thiokol was the producer of solid rocket boosters for all U.S. nuclear weapons) was promoted through the media, direct mailings, and the efforts of hundreds of local campaigns, and was featured in the mainstream press via Newsweek, the Cleveland Plain Dealer, and several radio talk shows. The boycott lasted for several years and had a notable impact on the company. Other projects include the Nuclear Free Home Project, which marketed lightbulbs and smoke detectors made by non nuclear-affiliated companies and contained no radioactive material. Materials include project files, correspondence, promotional materials, budgets, and graphic design files.
  - Aerospace Industries Association (AIA) conflict, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 13.02)
  - Aerospace Industries Association (AIA) conflict, 1989 (Box-folder 13.03)
  - Consumer Guide to the Nuclear Arms Race, 1985 (Box-folder 13.04)
  - "Free Zone" video project, 1989-1996 (Box-folder 13.05)
  - Morton Salt boycott, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 13.06)
  - Nuclear Free America international outreach, 1982-1992 (Box-folder 13.07)
  - Nuclear Divestment campaign, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 13.08)
  - Nuclear Free Home Project - lightbulbs, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 13.09)
  - Nuclear Free Home Project - smoke detectors, 1979-1992 (Box-folder 13.10)
  - Nuclear Free Zone Network, undated (Box-folder 13.11)
  - Nuclear Waste Democracy Project, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 13.12)
  - Radio documentary on Nuclear Free Zones, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 13.13)
  - "Reach Out and Touch a Nuclear Weapons Contractor" project, undated (Box-folder 13.14)
  - "Waste Land" video project, 1994 (Box-folder 13.15)
  - World Court Project, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 13.16)
  - World Court Project, undated (Box-folder 13.17)
  - World Court Project, 1993-1995 (Box-folder 13.18)
- Related Organizations, 1983-2000; Series 5
  Series 5 collects materials from a number of affiliated activist and social justice organizations both small and large. These include Concerned Citizens for Nuclear Safety, Greenpeace, International Peace Bureau, the Indigenous Environmental Network, Japan Council against Atomic and Hydrogen Bombs, NukeWatch, the Peace Boat, SANE/Freeze, and the World Information Service on Energy (WISE). Topics span a huge range of nuclear concerns, including waste disposal, power plant siting, construction, accidents, environmental protection, nonproliferation, disarmament, uranium mining, and international relations. Materials include newspapers, newsletters, white papers, flyers, brochures, conference papers, reports, and other ephemera. Many of the periodicals included are quite rare, as they were produced by small organizations with limited reach and a community focus; others are commonly available and produced by larger organizations with wider membership. Nuclear concerns are covered from many different angles, including legal, religious, and environmental directions.
  - Organizations: A, 1984-1995 (Box-folder 14.01)
  - Organizations: A, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 14.02)
  - Organizations: B, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 14.03)
  - Organizations: C, 1985-1995 (Box-folder 14.04)
  - Organizations: C, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 14.05)
  - Organizations: C, 1990-2000 (Box-folder 14.06)
  - Organizations: D, 1988-1995 (Box-folder 14.07)
  - Organizations: E, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 14.08)
  - Organizations: F, 1983-2000 (Box-folder 14.09)
  - Organizations: G, 1985-1990 (Box-folder 14.10)
  - Organizations: I, 1990-1993 (Box-folder 14.11)
  - Organizations: I, 1989-2001 (Box-folder 14.12)
  - Organizations: J, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 14.13)
  - Organizations: L, 2000 (Box-folder 14.14)
  - Organizations: M, 1990-1994 (Box-folder 14.15)
  - Organizations: N, undated (Box-folder 14.16)
  - Organizations: N, 1990-1996 (Box-folder 14.17)
  - Organizations: O, undated (Box-folder 14.18)
  - Organizations: P, 1987-1995 (Box-folder 14.19)
  - Organizations: P, 1989-1990 (Box-folder 14.20)
  - Organizations: P, undated (Box-folder 14.21)
  - Organizations: R, undated (Box-folder 14.22)
  - Organizations: S, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 15.01)
  - Organizations: S, 1989-1994 (Box-folder 15.02)
  - Organizations: T, undated (Box-folder 15.03)
  - Organizations: U, 1987-1994 (Box-folder 15.04)
  - Organizations: V, 1983-1994 (Box-folder 15.05)
  - Organizations: W, undated (Box-folder 15.06)
  - Organizations: W, undated (Box-folder 15.07)
  - Organizations: Numerical titles, undated (Box-folder 15.08)
  - Directories of allied organizations, undated (Box-folder 15.09)
  - Grassroots Peace Directory: Midatlantic, March 1988 (Box-folder 15.10)
  - Grassroots Peace Directory: New England, March 1988 (Box-folder 15.11)
  - Grassroots Peace Directory: New York, March 1988 (Box-folder 15.12)
  - Grassroots Peace Directory: Upper Midwest, March 1988 (Box-folder 15.13)
  - Grassroots Peace Directory: Addenda, March 1989 (Box-folder 15.14)
  - Grassroots Peace Directory: Midwest, April 1989 (Box-folder 15.15)
  - Grassroots Peace Directory: Southwestern, April 1989 (Box-folder 15.16)
  - Grassroots Peace Directory: Western, April 1989 (Box-folder 15.17)
- Subject Files, 1988-2000; Series 6
  Series 6 contains similar materials to those found in Series 5, but are arranged by subject focus. Flyers, brochures, pamphlets, newsclippings, and articles on a number of areas of concern are in this series. Files on the Hanford Site and the Trojan Nuclear Power Plant document Pacific Northwest issues, and more general files on topics such as pro-nuclear campaigns and economic justice show the breadth and depth of Nuclear Free America's concerns.
  - Activism, undated (Box-folder 15.18)
  - Activism - petitioning of elected officials, undated (Box-folder 15.19)
  - Activism - Religion, undated (Box-folder 15.20)
  - "Blue Ribbon" Commission on Nuclear Waste, 1993-1994 (Box-folder 15.21)
  - Cold War/Post Cold War, undated (Box-folder 15.22)
  - Comprehensive Test Ban, undated (Box-folder 15.23)
  - Economic justice, undated (Box-folder 15.24)
  - Economic justice, undated (Box-folder 15.25)
  - Environmentalism, undated (Box-folder 15.26)
  - Foreign arms sales, undated (Box-folder 15.27)
  - Hanford Site, 1989-1991 (Box-folder 15.28)
  - High Frequency Active Auroral Research Program (HAARP), undated (Box-folder 15.29)
  - Japan, undated (Box-folder 15.30)
  - Legislation, undated (Box-folder 15.31)
  - Legislation - Clean Water Act, 1994 (Box-folder 16.01)
  - Legislation - Nuclear Waste Policy Act, 1995 (Box-folder 16.02)
  - Middle East, undated (Box-folder 16.03)
  - Mixed oxide (MOX) fuels, undated (Box-folder 16.04)
  - Monitoring of nuclear sites/production, undated (Box-folder 16.05)
  - Non-nuclear energy sources, undated (Box-folder 16.06)
  - Non-nuclear weapons, undated (Box-folder 16.07)
  - Nuclear non-proliferation/disarmament, undated (Box-folder 16.08)
  - Nuclear non-proliferation/disarmament, undated (Box-folder 16.09)
  - Nuclear reactor designs, undated (Box-folder 16.10)
  - Nuclear power, undated (Box-folder 16.11)
  - Nuclear terrorism, undated (Box-folder 16.12)
  - Nuclear waste management, undated (Box-folder 16.13)
  - Nuclear waste management, undated (Box-folder 16.14)
  - Nuclear waste management, undated (Box-folder 16.15)
  - Nuclear waste management, undated (Box-folder 16.16)
  - Nuclear waste management, undated (Box-folder 16.17)
  - Nuclear waste management, undated (Box-folder 16.18)
  - Nuclear weapons testing, 1990-1995 (Box-folder 16.19)
  - Philanthropy, undated (Box-folder 16.20)
  - Political cartoons, undated (Box-folder 16.21)
  - Pro-nuclear campaigns, undated (Box-folder 16.22)
  - Public polling, undated (Box-folder 16.23)
  - Radiation exposure, undated (Box-folder 16.24)
  - Radioactive materials mining, undated (Box-folder 17.01)
  - Strategic Defense Initiative (Star Wars), undated (Box-folder 17.02)
  - Trojan Nuclear Power Plant, undated (Box-folder 17.03)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box-folder 17.04)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1988-1994 (Box-folder 17.05)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1989-2000 (Box-folder 17.06)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box-folder 17.07)
  - Photographs, undated (Box-folder 17.08)
- Artifacts and Memorabilia, 1945-1996; Series 7
  Series 7 is comprised of antinuclear ephemera, artifacts, and memorabilia collected by Nuclear Free America, including buttons, placards, posters, armbands, coffee mugs, stickers, and signs. Most are related to Nuclear Free Zones at various localities, but other national and international organizations represented include Bike for Peace and Movement de la Paix.
  - Antinuclear buttons gathered by Albert Donnay, circa 1969-1996 (Box-folder 17.09)
  - Antinuclear stickers, 1980-1996 (Box-folder 17.10)
    Includes stamps and bumper stickers.
  - Artifacts, 1945-1992 (Box-folder 17.11)
    Two coffee mugs, and a roof tile found at Nagasaki after the bomb.
  - Large signs and posters, circa 1985-1990 (Box-folder 20.1)
- Video Recordings, 1979-2003; Series 8
  This series contains VHS tape recordings of television productions and broadcasts related to nuclear issues. Notable items include an interview with spiritual leader Ram Dass in which he comments on nuclear free zones, as well as recordings related to tribal lands and nuclear activity.
  - "Free Zone: Democracy Meets the Nuclear Threat", 1989 (Box-item 18.01)
  - "Countdown to Meltdown", undated (Box-item 18.02)
  - "Another Trojan Horse" CBS Saturday Morning, Nov. 26th 1995 (Box-item 18.03)
  - "Everything is Connected to Radioactive Reservations", undated (Box-item 18.04)
  - Giveaway Songs, undated (Box-item 18.05)
  - "What's the Deal with Yucca Mountain?", 1994 (Box-item 18.06)
  - "Free Zone: Democracy Breaks the Nuclear Cycle", 1989 (Box-item 18.07)
  - "Waste Land: The Nuclear Free Indian Lands Project", circa 1993 (Box-item 18.08)
  - "Radiation Hazards - Hero", 1987 (Box-item 18.09)
  - FFTF Public Testimony, 1997 (Box-item 18.10)
  - "Columbia's Troubled Waters", 2003 (Box-item 18.11)
  - Pluto's Fire, undated (Box-item 18.12)
  - Paul Jacobs and the Nuclear Gang, 1979 (Box-item 18.13)
  - "The Water in Our Backyard", undated (Box-item 18.14)
  - Ram Dass on NFZ's, undated (Box-item 18.15)
  - "My Name is Allegany County", undated (Box-item 18.16)
  - '92 Masters (Couples) Part II, 1992 (Box-item 18.17)
  - Songs of Sovereignty, undated (Box-item 18.18)
  - "California's Water & Radioactive Waste", undated (Box-item 18.19)
  - "Sadako and the Thousand Paper Cranes", 1990 (Box-item 18.20)
  - "Hiroshima: A Mother's Prayer", undated (Box-item 18.21)
  - America's Defense Monitor, undated (Box-item 18.22)
  - "Nuclear Power Industry Transportation Claims Debunked" 1992 (Box-item 18.23)
  - "Withdraw from U.S. Bases! Appeal from Okinawa", undated (Box-item 18.24)
  - G. Smith Press Conference, 1995 (Box-item 18.25)
  - "How to Site a Dump with Roger Kasperson", 1989 (Box-item 18.26)
- Electronic Records, circa 1985-1995; Series 9 (Box 19)
  This series consists of floppy disks (both 5.5 inch and 3.5 inch), CD-ROMs, data tapes, and other electronic formats used in the administration of Nuclear Free America. These records are unprocessed and unavailable to researchers.